James Weldon Jones papers, Inclusive: 1917-1919, circa 2010, Bulk: 1917-1919
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
James Weldon Jones papers
Inclusive: 1917-1919, circa 2010, Bulk: 1917-1919
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3856
Jones, Alexander Bumpass "Tip", 1868 - 1963
One document box.
The James Weldon Jones papers contain a series of letters sent from Alexander "Tip" Jones to his son James Weldon Jones while the latter was serving in the United States Army during World War I.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Alexander Bumpass “Tip” Jones was born on 1868 April 10 in Copeville, Texas. He was the son of James Edwin Jones and Nancy Adams Bumpass. As indicated by letters to his son, Alexander pursued a career in the cattle business. On 1893 April 9, the day before his twenty-fifth birthday, Alexander married Lula Yeary. The couple had four children over the course of their marriage: David, James Weldon, Pat Neff, and Nannie “Tippie.” The eldest child passed away at the age of three, but the three youngest children all reached adulthood. Alexander passed away in Quanah, Texas, on 1963 March 2.
James Weldon Jones, the second oldest child of Alexander and Lula Jones, was born on 1896 February 28 in the same town as his father. Along with his younger brother Pat, James attended Baylor University in the late 1910s. James was particularly involved in Baylor community life. In addition to serving as the junior class poet and the Vice President of the Student Self Government Association, James was a member of a debate team, the university chorus, and the Panhandle Club.
In 1917, when the United States entered World War I on the side of the Allies, James enlisted in the United States Army as a private. The bulk of this collection contains letters sent from Alexander Jones to his son James as the latter trained in San Antonio and eventually sailed overseas to France.
James Weldon Jones survived the Great War and returned to the United States. Later in life, he earned political appointments in both the Truman and Eisenhower administrations. From 1934 to 1940, he served as the Insular Auditor and Financial Adviser to the High Commissioner as well as Acting High Commissioner to the Philippines. From 1941 to 1955, Jones acted as the Assistant Director of the Bureau of the Budget.
James passed away on 1982 November 24 in Harris County, Texas. He was buried in Arlington National Cemetery in Virginia.
Scope and Content
The James Weldon Jones papers span from 1917 to 2010. The correspondence series, which consists of letters written from Alexander Bumpass "Tip" Jones to his son James Weldon Jones, ranges from 1917 to 1919. James Weldon Jones joined the American military effort in World War I and the materials in the first series represent his father's attempts to keep in contact with him.
The literary productions series consists of one folder of biographical materials collected by an unknown source. Included in this folder are genealogical materials for the Jones family, bibliographic citations for other James Weldon Jones materials, and a xeroxed photograph of James Weldon Jones' gravestone.
Arrangement
Prior to processing, the James Weldon Jones papers consisted of nine folders. Although there was no inventory, the materials had been organized chronologically with the original letters placed in acid-free sheet protectors.
An inventory and preliminary processing plan have since been created. The original organization has been maintained.
There are two series in this collection: I. Correspondence and II. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3856. Acquired 2013-06-06
Related Resources
Related references
“Baylor Men in Military Service.” The Baylor Bulletin, vol. XXI, no. 5&6 (1918 December).
The Baylor Round-up. Waco: Baylor University Press, 1917.
The Harry S. Truman Library and Museum. “James Weldon Jones Papers.” Accessed 2013 July 1.
James Weldon Jones Papers, Accession #3856, Box #1, Folder #10, The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
W.R. Poage Legislative Library. “About Ben Guttery.” Accessed 2013 July 1.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Baylor University -- History, Military.
Subjects
World War, 1914-1918 -- United States.
Genres
Correspondence.
- Correspondence, 1917-1919
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series, the largest in the collection, contains nine folders of correspondence from the World War I era. The letters are all addressed from Alexander Bumpass "Tip" Jones to his son, Private James Weldon Jones of the United States Army. The materials are organized chronologically and are in good condition. The original letters are each accompanied by Xerox copies.
  - “Tip” Jones to James Weldon Jones, 1917 December 9-23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - “Tip” Jones to James Weldon Jones, 1917 December 25-31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - “Tip” Jones to James Weldon Jones, 1918 January 3-29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “Tip” Jones to James Weldon Jones, 1918 January 31-February 20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - “Tip” Jones to James Weldon Jones, 1918 February 25-April 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - “Tip” Jones to James Weldon Jones, 1918 May 9-June 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - “Tip” Jones to James Weldon Jones, 1918 July 6-August 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - “Tip” Jones to James Weldon Jones, 1918 August 25-October 11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - “Tip” Jones to James Weldon Jones, 1918 November 10-1919 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Literary Productions, circa 2010
  General condition: Excellent.
  The literary productions series, which consists of one folder of biographical materials, was compiled by an unknown source. The latest materials in the packet of information are dated 2010. Included are brief notes concerning the Jones family, citations of other James Weldon Jones materials across the nation, and a Xeroxed photograph of James Weldon Jones' gravestone.
  - Biographical Materials: Jones Family, circa 2010 (Box 1, Folder 10)